[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right,
this is CS50 And this
is the day we take off the
proverbial training wheels, namely
the CS50 library.
You'll recall last week as
we focused on algorithms,
we started focusing on lots of
comparisons and lots of swapping.
And we did that fairly algorithmically,
fairly conceptually last week.
but today we're going to
focus on actually doing
that a little more mechanically,
a little more methodically.
And I thought this would be easier
to take the training wheels off,
hopefully not a metaphor for today.
OK.
So [CHUCKLE] what we'll do
first though, is learn how
to count in a slightly different way.
You'll recall in Week
0 we did this already
whereby we introduced not only the
human decimal system-- with which
everyone's familiar --but also binary.
It turns out there's other base
systems where you don't just
use powers of 10 or 2, you use
other base systems entirely as well.
And this is useful because
today when we focus really
on the computer's memory,
and later today on files--
the actual creation of
and editing of files,
like images you might have on
your own phones or computers
--it turns out it's very useful
to be able to address the memory
inside of our computers
or phones-- that is assign
a number, a unique
identifier, to every byte
so that we can just talk about
where things are in memory.
Now you might think we would do 0, 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13,
14, 15, but it turns out that's
not actually human convention.
There's nothing wrong with this.
It's correct but you're about to see
today a slightly different syntax where
we do count from 0 to 1, to 2, to 3,
to 4, to 5, to 6, to 7, to 8, to 9,
but in the world of not decimal,
not binary, but hexadecimal-- hex
meaning 16.
Can you actually count higher than nine?
There is the letter A,
B, C, D, E and F. Why?
While using these individual
alphabetical letters, can
you effectively count not
only from 0 through 9--
using single digits --but
also 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15--
F, representing 15.
And so I introduce this because we'll
see this pattern throughout today
and throughout the coming weeks
programs where the computer will just
very conventionally display to you
numbers not in decimal, not in binary,
but sometimes in hexadecimal.
But we'll see why that
is in just a moment.
Indeed, in binary we
had the digits 0 and 1,
decimal we had 0 through
9, in hexadecimal--
to recap --we have 0 through
F, where again, F is 15.
So how does this actually work?
Just a quick whirlwind tour,
this was our notation in binary.
And I had eight 0 bits here,
bit meaning binary digit.
And based on the columns
there, we had powers of 2,
or if we multiplied that out,
the ones place over there,
the 128's place over here.
This of course, if you do the
math, is what number in decimal?
So just 0-- right --if you multiply
the columns by the numbers they're in.
But what about this?
If I change all those 0s
to 1s, what was the highest
we could count in binary
if we had eight bits?
AUDIENCE: 255
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, 255
was the highest we can count.
You might say 256 but again,
if you start counting at 0,
you sort of spend one of
those numbers as the 0.
So 255 is the highest you
can count with eight bits.
And we could do the math if we cared.
128 times 1 plus 64
times 1, and so forth.
But let me just stipulate,
that's indeed 255.
In decimal, and indeed in decimal,
we would represent the columns
as powers of 10 or ones place, ten
place, hundreds place, and so forth.
So that's all Week 0 stuff.
It turns out, though, that there's
another way of representing 255
in decimal using hexadecimal, except now
instead of powers of 2 or powers of 10,
we're just going to use powers of 16.
And it turns out this is convenient
for reasons related to computing.
So the rightmost column will be our
16th to the zeroth or the ones place.
The second column will be our 16s place.
And remember, F, individually
represents 15 in decimal.
So we can count quite similarly.
So this in hexadecimal would just be 0.
16 times 0, plus 1
times 0, is of course 0.
This of course, easy
one, is what number?
AUDIENCE: 1
DAVID J. MALAN: 1 in decimal.
This is going to be 2,
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
And whereas in the decimal
role would you want to say 10--
or 1, 0 --here we can actually count
a little higher to A, B, C, D, E, F--
and that represents 15.
Why?
16 times 0, plus 1 times
F-- which again, F is 15.
So 1 times F--
or 15-- gives you 15.
Now how do you count as high as 16?
Well, you can probably
envision it already, right?
You kind of carry the 1 just
like in decimal and binary.
So in hexadecimal, 1,
0 is the number 16.
And here's where you
just have to be careful.
You shouldn't say 10 anymore.
That's a decimal number.
This is 1, 0 in hexadecimal.
But we can count higher.
If this is 16, this is 17, 18, 19, 20,
21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30,
31.
And once you need 32, that's going to
require another digit, if you will.
So very low level.
And none of us really on staff
sort of think in hexadecimal,
you'll just see things in hexadecimal.
And all this is to say is
that it can be converted back
to the more familiar decimal
or any other system as well.
Higher than that we would go 2, 0,
which of course, is 16 times 2--
which is 32 --plus 0.
So it turns out that if you have four 1s
and four 1s that it can be represented
as FF, you've actually seen FF and
probably 00 and other alphabetical
characters before.
How many of you have ever done
web design using HTML, CSS?
So like at least a third
or so of the class.
And for those unfamiliar,
we'll get to that
if you want to pursue that
track later in the semester
but recall RGB from Week 0.
Red, green, blue refers to
how computers can represent
the colors of every pixel using some
amount of red, some amount of green,
some amount of blue.
Well it turns out it's
just human convention
to describe the amounts of red,
green, and blue in a color in terms
of hexadecimal digits-- where this
means give me no red, no green, no blue.
And if you think back to Week 0 that's
actually going to give us black.
If you have none of those three colors,
it's just the absence of those colors
and you get black.
If however, you have FF--
which is what?
--255 amount of red, that's a
lot of red, and 0 green, 0 blue.
So if a computer were to represent
a pixel on your screen as red
it would store FF0000.
That is a lot of red, no green, no blue.
Meanwhile, if you had
this representation,
this is why this is green.
This would be blue.
And if you combine all
three colors a lot--
a lot of red, lot of
green, lot of blue --this
is how a computer would represent white.
And so we'll come back to this
later on in game development,
and web development, and mobile--
if of interest-- but notice that this
is just a common convention as well.
So if we reconsider what
our memory looks like,
it's just this big grid of bytes.
And we might describe the top one is 0
and the bottom one in this case as 1F.
And we can just keep counting.
However, at first glance it
might be a little ambiguous.
Am I looking at decimal?
Am I looking at hexadecimal?
Am I looking at something
else altogether?
So humans years ago decided
that just to avoid ambiguity,
if you are using hexadecimal,
the human convention
is to prefix every digit on the
screen with 0x, just arbitrarily.
The 0x means nothing mathematically.
It just means here comes
a hexadecimal value.
So you can disambiguate it from
something like decimal itself.
Whew.
OK.
That was a mouthful.
And that's it for base systems.
There's no more something
decimals here on out this term.
Slight white lie, there's
something called octal
but we probably won't look at that.
Are there any questions at all?
No, all right.
So how can we actually
use this information?
Well let's now see
some examples of what's
going on truly inside of
your computer's memory.
And we'll see where
hexadecimal is germane
and how we can now start manipulating
things more carefully inside
of the computer's memory.
This of course, is just a line of code
involving creation of a variable called
n.
And that variable is having
stored in it, the value 50.
So let's go ahead and whip up a
quick program that does exactly this.
I'm going to go ahead
and call this address dot
c, just to convey that we're
going to be playing with addresses
in the computer's memory.
And I'm going to go ahead
and keep it simple at first,
include standard I/O dot
h and then int main void.
And then down here, super
simple, int n gets 50.
And then I'm going to
go ahead and print out,
percent i comma n, thereby
printing this value.
So this too is sort of Week 1 stuff,
whereby when I run this program now
after saving it, make address--
seems to compile OK --dot slash
address, I should see of course, 50.
All right, just the number
50 in that variable.
All right.
So you're probably comfortable with
these kinds of exercises thus far.
But it turns out that we
can now kind of infer what's
going on inside the computer's memory.
If this again is my computer's
memory and somewhere in there
I have a variable n, it might
take up four bytes down there.
An int recall is four bytes so
I'm going to go ahead and use
four squares on the screen.
For consistency, I'm going to call
it n and just put the number 50.
Now if you really look underneath
the hood, that's not 50 per se,
it's like 32 bits, 0s and 1s
that represent the number 50.
But again, we don't care about
transistors in that low level detail
now.
But when I go ahead and
print this, all I'm doing
is printing the contents
of that variable called n.
But that variable technically does
exist at a specific address in memory.
Right?
If the top left hand corner was 0
and the bottom right hand corner
was a bigger number-- and
maybe this is out of context.
I'm sort of zoomed out because
you might have billions
of bytes of memory in your computer.
Suppose for the sake of discussion that
that variable n and the value therein,
50 is technically at address 0x meaning
hexadecimal 12345678, wherever that is.
It's a big arbitrary number.
But it indeed exists somewhere
in your computer's memory so long
as you have that many
bytes of hardware to use.
Well it turns out that
using C we can actually--
no pun intended --see
this value as well.
Let me go ahead and
tweak this code slightly.
I'm not going to go ahead
and print out n this time,
I'm going to go ahead and
print out ampersand n, which
happens to be a new
piece of syntax for C.
But it quite simply means
the AddressOf operator.
So wherever n is, go ahead and
figure out what its address is,
it's location in memory.
And it turns out C has a
special format code for this.
Instead of percent i, it's
percent p, where percent p
is going to print that address for us.
So let me go ahead and save that make
address again to recompile and then do
dot slash address, enter.
And voila.
Now it just so happens that in CS50
IDE running on this cloud server,
it's not address 0x12345678.
I just made that up for
the sake of discussion.
It's technically at 0x7FFE00B3ADBC,
which has no meaning to us
here in class but it is all
hexadecimal because every digit there
is 0 through F.
So it's kind of cool.
This doesn't seem like
useful information yet
but you can in fact see where values
are inside of your computer's memory.
Well, what is that value?
Well it turns out that
as soon as you ask
the computer for the
address of some value,
you are getting what's called
a pointer to that value.
A pointer is effectively an
address in the computer's memory.
And that's why it's percent p.
This is telling printf,
go ahead and print for me
a pointer, the address of some value.
And by convention again, it's
displayed in hexadecimal like that.
Well, it turns out we can
actually undo these effects.
Let me go ahead and
make one change here.
Suppose that now I want to go
ahead and print out 50 again.
I can actually reverse the
effects of this operator.
So ampersand n means to
go get the address of n.
But it turns out there's
another operator in C that's
quite useful around now
and that's this one here.
So whereas ampersand is our
so-called AddressOf operator, --star,
or an asterisk--
we've seen before in multiplication.
And today it has a different
meaning in a different context.
The star is the opposite
of the AddressOf operator,
it says go to a specific address.
So whereas, an ampersand
means what's the address,
star means go to an address.
So if I want to print out
now, not the address per se,
but I literally want to
print out the value in n,
ergo using percent i, I can
actually undo what I literally did,
stupidly-- but for the sake of
demonstration --by doing star
ampersand n.
Why?
The ampersand says, what's the address?
The star says, go to that address.
So it effectively just
undoes the operation.
So you wouldn't want
to use this in practice
but it just speaks to the sort of
basic operations that we're doing here.
So make address, let me go ahead and
say now, dot slash address, enter.
And what should I see this time?
50, because I'm not even
showing the address.
I'm getting the address and going to the
address, thereby defeating the point.
I again see 50.
But this is only to say quite simply
that even though things might seem
a little cryptic today at
first glance, syntactically,
ampersand is get the address, star is go
to that address, one way or the other.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Can you [INAUDIBLE]
by typing the address
in [INAUDIBLE] like a [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID J. MALAN: Really
good question, yes.
So if I had remembered the
address, maybe it was 0x12345678,
I could actually hard code
that address in my program
and tell the computer to go there.
The syntax is a little different.
I would have to coerce it using a cast
but I could make that happen, yes.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: What happens if you don't
know even the type of the variable?
Can you [INAUDIBLE]
without knowing that?
DAVID J. MALAN: Ah,
really good question.
What if you don't know
the type of the variable,
what format code would
you therefore use?
Short answer, you have to decide.
To a computer, everything in
memory is just bits, 0s and 1s, how
you display them is entirely up to you.
So if you don't know what
they are, you can only
guess, or tell the
computer arbitrarily to say
it's a char, a float, an
int, or something else.
It can't figure that out
for you, at least in C.
All right.
So let's just go ahead
now and make more clear
where we can store information here.
Let me go ahead and change
this code. now as follows.
It turns out that you can actually store
addresses and variables themselves.
I don't have to just do
this ampersand thing here.
Let me go ahead and change
the program as follows.
Let me go ahead and declare another
variable called p and store in it's
the address of n.
So again, nothing new here, just says,
ampersand n, go get the address of n.
But I do have to do
something different here.
On the left hand side is
the name of my variable.
I've called it p, for pointer.
But if you want to store
the address of some value
in a variable you have to specify
not just the type of value that's
in that other variable,
you have to specify
with this star operator in a very
confusing, unfortunate, different
context, that this is a pointer.
So whereas n has a data type of
int-- just as it has since Week 0
--the only thing new now is that it
turns out there's another type of data
that you can describe as a pointer.
And a pointer is denoted with
this star and the int just
means this is the pointer to an
int or it is the address of an int.
And we'll see later
we can do floats and--
floats, and chars, and bunches
of other data types too.
This just means that p is
a variable that's going
to contain a pointer to an int, a.k.a.
The address of an int.
All right.
So what can I do now
with this information?
Well let me go ahead and
print out either of these.
If I want to go ahead and print out
now, for instance, that address,
I can go ahead and print % p
and print out p just like this.
Let me go ahead and
make address, enter--
seems to compile OK --run address.
And I'm going to see something
cryptic again, 0x 7FFF3977662C, which
is different from before
but that's because one
of the features of modern
computers is actually
to move things around in memory for
you, which is a security feature.
But more on that perhaps, later on.
But it's still a big
cryptic hexadecimal address.
What if though, just for
the sake of demonstration,
I didn't want to print out the
address because rarely after today
are we going to care about the
specific addresses where things are?
How could I change line 7 here
to print out, not the value of p,
but what is at the location p?
How do I go to the location in p?
OK.
Star p, I heard.
So instead of printing
p itself, I say star p.
I change the format
code just to be an int.
OK.
Siri is trying to be helpful here.
But now I'm saying, go ahead
and print me an integer.
And the integer I want you
to print is the one at p.
Star means go to that
address, which is p.
So let me save this, make address.
All right, seems to compile.
Dot slash address,
let's see what happens.
And back to 50.
So we're just kind of jumping
through hoops at the moment,
accomplishing nothing real yet.
But again, just demonstrating,
and applying, and reversing
the effects of these two operators.
Any questions thus far on these
addresses, or pointers, or the like?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So there's six lines
where you stored the address of n--
DAVID J. MALAN: Mm hmm.
AUDIENCE: --pointer of p.
DAVID J. MALAN: You stored
the address of n in p and p
is a pointer, specifically
a pointer to an integer.
Put another way, p is the
address of an integer.
Which integer?
n
AUDIENCE: Could I just write--
what would happen if I just
write int p instead of int star p?
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
If you said int p equals ampersand
n semicolon, instead of int star p,
Clang-- the compiler --would actually
yell at you because it realizes that,
wait a minute, you're trying to store
an address, not an integer like you
and I know it, 12345678.
Even though technically
they are numbers,
Clang is smart enough to
realize that if you're
getting the address of something,
you must store it in a pointer.
You cannot store it in just an integer.
All right.
So let's make this a little more visual.
So if this is again
my computer's memory,
let me go ahead and pull
up the slide from before.
And the goal at hand is to visualize
really these two lines of code.
Give me a variable called
n and store in it 50--
just like Week 1 --then also give me
a variable called p and store in it
the address of n.
That's now in Week 4.
What does this look like?
Well, my computer's memory.
Let's go ahead and put
n on the screen again.
And n might be down there
arbitrarily somewhere in memory.
And it's called n, the value is 50.
Technically, that 50 is somewhere.
And let's just arbitrarily for
discussion sake, say it address
0x 12345678, so somewhere arbitrary.
What does p look like in this picture?
Well p is a variable, which
means it's a bunch of bits
that can store information.
And let's just propose that
they're up here in the middle.
This variable is called p.
What value is p storing?
It's literally storing 0x12345678, which
is again, the address of the value n.
So that's all that's going on here.
But honestly, this is
getting so low level.
And even my sort of
eyes are glazing over
as we start talking about
these low level details.
Turns out that pointers lend
themselves to abstraction.
And in fact, we can
start to do that already.
Let's just focus now in the absence
of memory, just on these two values.
This big rectangle here
represents a variable
called p, which stores an address.
This rectangle here
represents another variable
called n that storing the number 50.
Technically speaking,
I don't really want
to care moving forward
what address of n is.
I just want you to know
that I can access it.
And so would a computer
scientist would typically
do is never talk about
specific addresses--
certainly never write them down like
I have thus far --but instead, just
literally draw an
arrow that conceptually
says that this variable p is
pointing at the number 50.
And we can very quickly
start to move away
from the actual addresses in question.
And in fact, we can visualize
this even a little metaphorically.
So for instance, here is,
for instance, a mailbox.
And suppose that this is address 123.
What is in address 123?
Well it's a variable
of type int, called n,
looks like it's storing the number 50.
Right?
We saw these letters--
these numbers last week.
So here's the number 50, which is an
integer inside of this variable, today,
represented as a mailbox
instead of as a locker.
Well suppose that this mailbox over
here is not n but suppose this is p.
And it happens to be an address 456.
But who really cares?
If this variable p is a pointer to an
integer, namely that one over there,
when I open this door,
what am I going to find?
Well I'm hoping I find
the equivalent of-- we
picked these up at the Coop
earlier --the equivalent
of a conceptual pointer saying
the number n is over there.
But what specifically, at a lower
level, is actually inside this mailbox
if that variable n is at location 0x123?
What's probably inside this mailbox?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
the address, indeed, 123.
So it's sort of like a
treasure map if you will.
Oh, I have to go to
123 to get this value.
Oh, the integer in
question is indeed 50.
And that's the fundamental difference.
This is the int that happens to be
inside of this variable of type int.
This is the address that's a pointer
that's in this other variable, p,
but that is conceptually, simply
pointing from one variable
to another, thereby giving any
sort of conceptual breadcrumbs.
And we'll see-- frankly, in one
week --how amazingly powerful it is.
When you can have one piece
of memory pointing at another,
pointing at another,
you can start to construct very
sophisticated data structures,
as they're called,
things like family trees,
and lists, and other data structures
that you might have heard of.
Or even if you haven't, these will
be the underpinnings next week
of all of today's fanciest
algorithms used by,
certainly the Googles,
and the Facebooks,
and the Microsofts of the world
to manage large data sets.
That's where we're going next
week, in terms of application.
So questions about that representation?
Yeah, in the middle.
AUDIENCE: Does that mean that your
memory has to be twice as big?
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry
can you say it once more?
AUDIENCE: Is that to say your memory has
to be twice as big to store pointers?
DAVID J. MALAN: Ah,
really good question.
Is it the case that your
pointers need to be twice as big?
Not necessarily, just, this
is the way life is these days.
On most modern Macs and PCs, pointers
use 64 bits-- the equivalent of a long,
if you recall that brief
discussion in Week 1.
So I deliberately drew
my pointer on the screen
here as taking up 8 bytes or 64 bits.
I've deliberately drawn my integer
n as taking up 4 bytes or 32 bits.
That is convention these
days on modern hardware.
But it's not necessarily the case.
Frankly, I could not find a
bigger mailbox at Home Depot,
so we went with two identical
different colored ones.
So metaphor is imperfect.
All right.
So moving from this to something
more familiar now, if you will.
Recall that we've been talking
about strings for quite some time.
And in fact, most of the interesting
programs we've written thus far
involve maybe input from the
human and some form of text
that you are then manipulating.
But string we said in Week
1 is a bit of a white lie.
I mean, it is the training
wheels that I promised
we would start taking off today.
So let's consider what a string
actually is now in this new context.
So if we have a string like EMMA
here, declared in a variable
called s, and quote unquote, EMMA in all
caps, as we've done a couple of times
now.
What does this actually look
like inside of the computer?
Well somewhere in my computer's memory
there are four, nay, five bytes,
storing E-M-M-A, and then additionally,
that null terminating character that
demarcates where the
end of the string is.
This is just eight individual 0 bits.
So that's where EMMA might be
represented in the computer's memory.
But recall that the
variable in question was s.
That was my string.
And so that's why over
the past few weeks
any time you want to manipulate a
string, you use its name, like s.
And you can access bracket 0,
bracket 1, bracket 2, bracket 3,
to get at the individual characters
in that string like EMMA, E-M-M-A,
respectively.
But of course it's the case, especially
per today's revelation, that really,
all of those bytes have
their own addresses.
Right?
We're not going to care after
this week what those addresses are
but they certainly exist.
For instance, E might be at 0x123.
M might be at 0x124--
1 byte away --0x125, 0x126, 0x127.
They're deliberately 1 byte away
because remember a string is defined
by characters back-to-back-to-back.
So let's say for the sake of
discussion that EMMA name in memory
happens to start at 0x123.
Well, what then really
is that variable s?
Well, I dare say that s
is really just a pointer.
Right?
It can be a variable, depicted
here just as before, called s.
And it stores the value 0x123.
Why?
That's where Emma's name begins.
But of course, we don't really have
to care about this level of precision,
the actual numbers.
Let's just draw it as a picture.
s is, if you will, a pointer to
Emma's actual name in memory,
which might be down over here.
It might be over here.
It might be over here, depending
on where in the computer's memory
it ended up by chance.
But this arrow just suggests that
s is pointing to Emma, specifically
at the first letter in her name.
But that's sufficient though, right?
Because how-- if s stores the
beginning of Emma's name, 0x123.
And that's indeed where
the E is but we just
draw this pictorially with an arrow.
How does the computer
know where Emma's name
ends if all it's technically
remembering is the beginning?
AUDIENCE: The null
terminating character.
DAVID J. MALAN: The null
And we stipulated a couple of
weeks ago that that is important.
But now it's all the more
important because it turns out
that s, this thing we've
been calling a string,
has no familiarity with
MMA or the null terminator.
All s is pointing at
technically, as of today,
is the first letter in her name, which
happens to be in this story at 0x123.
But the computer is smart enough
to know that if you just point it
at the first letter in a
string, it can figure out
where the string ends by just looking--
as with a loop --for that
null terminating character.
So this is to say ultimately, that
there is no such thing as string.
And we'll see if this strikes a chord.
There is no such thing as a string.
This was a little white lie
we began telling in Week 1
just so that we could get interesting,
real work done, manipulating text.
But what is string most likely
implemented as would you say?
AUDIENCE: An array of characters.
DAVID J. MALAN: An array
of characters, yes.
But that was Week 1's definition.
What technically now, as
of today, must a string be?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry, over here.
AUDIENCE: A pointer.
DAVID J. MALAN: A pointer.
Right? s, the variable
in which I was storing
Emma's name would seem to
manifest a pattern just
like we saw with the numbers
a moment ago, the number 50.
s seems to be storing the
address of the first character
in that sequence of characters.
And so indeed, it would
seem to be a string.
Well, how do we actually
connect these dots?
Well suppose that we
have this line of code
again where we had int n equals 50.
And then we had this other
line of code where we said,
go ahead and create a variable called
p and store in it the address of n.
That's where we left off earlier.
But it turns out that this thing
here is our data type from Week 1.
This thing here, int star, is
a new data type as of today.
The variable stores, not an
int, but the address of an int.
It turns out that something like
this line of code, with Emma's name,
is synonymous with char star.
Right?
If a star represents an address and char
represents the type of address being
pointed at, just as int star can
let you point at a value like n--
which stored 50 --so could a char star--
by that same logic --allow you to
store the address of and therefore
point at a character.
And of course, as you
said, from Week 1, a string
is just a sequence of characters.
So a string would seem to be just
the address of the first byte
in the sequence of characters.
And the last byte happens to be all 0s
by convention, to help us find the end.
So what then more
technically is a string
and what is the CS50
library that we're now going
to start taking off as training wheels?
Well last week we introduced
you to the notion of typedef,
where you can create your own customized
data type that does not exist in C
but does exist in your own program.
And we introduced this keyword, typedef.
We proposed last week that this was
useful because you could actually
declare a fancy structure
that encapsulates
multiple variables,
like name and number,
and then we called this data
structure, last week, a person.
That was the new data type we invented.
Well it turns out you can use
typedef in exactly the same way
even more simply than we did
last week by saying this.
If you say typedef char star string--
typedef means give me a new
data type, just for my own use.
Char star means the type of value is
going to be the address of a character.
And the name I want to give to that
data type is going to be string.
And so literally, this
line of code here, this
is one of the lines of code
in CS50 dot h-- the header
file you've been including
for several weeks,
where we are creating a
data type called string
to make it a synonym for char star.
So that if you will,
it's an abstraction,
a simplification on top of the
idea of a sequence of characters
being pointed at by an address.
Any questions?
And honestly, this is
why-- and maybe those sort
of blank stares --this is why
we introduced strings in Week 1
as being an actual type as
opposed to not existing at all.
Because who really cares
about addresses and pointers
and all of that when all
you want to do is like,
print, hello world, or
hello, so and so's name?
Yeah, question.
AUDIENCE: What other-- what
other functions are created--
major functions are created
by CS50 are not intrinsic to--
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
We'll come back to this later today.
But other functions that are
defined in the CS50 library that
are training wheels that
come off today are getString,
getInt, getFloat, and the
other get functions as well.
But that's about it that we do for you.
Other questions?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Can you define
all of these words again?
Like, it's-- so string is like a
character pointer which points--
I was confused about that.
Can you repeat that?
DAVID J. MALAN: Sure.
A string, per this definition, is a
char star, as a programmer would say.
What does that mean?
A string is quite simply a variable that
contains the address of a character.
By our human convention, that
character might be the beginning
of a multi character sequence.
But that's what we
called strings in Week 1.
So a string is just the
address of a single character.
And we leave it to human convention
to know that the end of the string
will just be demarcated
by eight 0 bits, a.k.a.
the null terminator.
And this is the sense
in which-- especially
if you have some prior
programming experience
--that C is much more low level.
In Python, as you'll
soon see in a few weeks,
everything just works
so splendidly easily.
If you want a string,
you can have a string.
You don't have to worry about
any of these low level details.
But that's because Python
is built here, conceptually,
where C is built down here-- so to
speak --closer to the computer's memory.
But there's no magic.
If you want to string, fine.
Just remember where it starts,
remember where it ends.
And boom, you're done.
The star in the syntax today is just a
way of expressing those ideas in code.
So let's go ahead then and
experiment with this string,
just as we did a moment ago using
Emma's name now instead of an int.
So let me go ahead and
erase those lines earlier.
And let me go back to Week 1 style
stuff, where I just say string s
equals quote unquote, Emma.
And then of course, if I to print
this, I can simply say this as before.
So just as a quick safety check, let
me go ahead and make address again.
Whoops.
What did I do wrong?
Let me scroll up to the first--
of many it seems --errors.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: You're using
string, [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, I
kind of shouldn't have taken
off all the training wheels just yet.
I'm still using string.
So let me go ahead and put
that back just for now.
That will give me access
to that typedef for string.
Let me recompile it as make address.
That worked.
So that was the solution, thank you.
And then address again.
We just see Emma.
So what can we now do that's
a little bit different here?
Well, one, you know
what I can actually do?
I can get rid of this-- the
solution a moment ago --and say,
I don't need string anymore.
I don't need those training wheels.
If s is going to represent
a string, technically, s
is just going to store the
address of the first character.
And it suffices actually,
just to write this.
So literally instead of
string, you write char star.
Technically, you don't need--
you can have extra space
to the left or right.
But most programmers write it just as
I have here, char star variable name.
That looks scarier now but
it's no different from what
we've been doing for weeks.
If I now do make address
without the CS50 library,
still works, because C knows
what I'm talking about.
And if I run address
now, I still see Emma.
But now I can start to play around.
Right?
If s is the address of a
character, what was the format code
I can use to print an address?
Not percent i, but--
AUDIENCE: Percent p.
DAVID J. MALAN: Percent p, a pointer.
So let me go ahead and
recompile this now.
Make address, that compiles too.
And when I run dot slash address,
I'm not going to see Emma now.
What should I see instead?
Some address, right?
I have no idea what it is.
It looks like Emma's name
is stored at 0x42A9F2,
whatever that number translates
to decimal, somewhere
in the computer's memory.
But it turns out then
too, what about this?
Let me go ahead and add
another line of code and say,
you know what, I'm really curious now.
What is the address of the
first letter in Emma's name?
How do I express in C, the
first letter only of Emma's name
if Emma is stored in s.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: s bracket zero, right?
That would seem to be that.
But that is what?
That's a char. s bracket 0 is a char.
How do I get the address of s bracket 0?
AUDIENCE: Ampersand.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, I
can just say ampersand.
Right?
So it's ugly looking
but that's fine for now.
Make address, enter.
Whoops.
It's uglier because I
forgot my semicolon.
Let me go ahead and make
address again, enter.
Seems to compile.
And when I run dot slash address
now, notice I get the same thing.
And this is because C
is taking me literally.
When you print out s, a string,
it's technically just the address
of the first character.
And indeed, I can corroborate
as much by running s
bracket zero then get the
address of the first character.
And they are indeed one in the same.
So a string is this sort of abstraction
on top of a bunch of characters.
But again, s is just an address.
And that's all we're emphasizing now.
And if I get really curious--
not that you would necessarily
do this in a real
program --what if I print
out a few more characters in Emma's
name, like s bracket 1, 2, and 3?
Let me go ahead, just out of curiosity
and make this program and dot slash
address.
Now notice what I see, is
again, s's address is at 42AB52.
The first character in
s is at the same thing,
by definition of what a string is.
And then notice what's
kind of neat-- if this is--
if-- for some definition of
neat --53, 54, 55 is noteworthy.
Why?
They're one byte apart.
So this whole time, whenever you
implemented Caesar, or substitution,
or some other cipher in
problem set two, anytime
you were manipulating individual
characters-- you didn't know it
--but you were just visiting
different mailboxes.
You were just visiting different
addresses in the computer's memory
in order to manipulate them somehow.
All right.
Can I do one last demo that's
a little arcane and then
we'll make things more-- more real?
All right.
So it turns out if all that's
going on underneath the hood
is just addresses, watch
what I can do here.
If I want to go ahead and print
out what is at the address s,
what will I find in memory
if I go to the address in s?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry, a little louder.
AUDIENCE: The first letter.
DAVID J. MALAN: The first
letter in Emma's name, right?
If we can all agree-- even if
it's a little unfamiliar still
--that s is just the address of
a character, and I say, go to s,
what should I see specifically?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Probably
E in Emma Right?
If s is the address of the
first character of her name,
star s would mean go to that character.
So let me go ahead and
print that as a char.
So let me go ahead now and make
address dot slash address, enter.
There is the E because I can say, go
to that address and print what's there.
And I can actually do this for
all of her letters in her name.
Let me go ahead and print
out another one here.
So how do I get at the
second letter in Emma's name?
Previous-- normally, like last
week, we would have done this.
And that just magically gets you
to the second letter in her name.
But I can do it a little differently.
What if I go to s and
then, from where do I want
to go from s to get the second letter?
AUDIENCE: Plus one.
DAVID J. MALAN: Plus one, right?
I mean, maybe we can literally
just do arithmetic here.
If s is the address of her first letter,
it stands to reason that s plus 1
is the address of her second letter.
So make address now dot slash address.
And I should see EM.
And I can do this twice more maybe and
go ahead and do this and then this.
But this time add 2 and this time add
3, just doing some simple arithmetic.
Make address dot slash address, there is
Emma but in a much lower level detail.
So what is this bracket symbol?
In computer science, this is
what's called syntactic sugar.
It's kind of a silly name.
But it just refers to a handy feature
so that you, the programmer, can say,
s bracket 0 or bracket 1.
But what the computer is actually doing
underneath the hood-- the compiler,
Clang --it's actually converting all of
your uses of square brackets since Week
1 to this format here.
It's just doing arithmetic
underneath the hood.
Now you don't have to
do this moving forward.
But I point out this low level
detail just to give you a sense of,
there really is no magic.
When you say, go print
an address or go do this,
the computer is taking you literally.
Whew.
OK, that was a lot.
Yes, question.
AUDIENCE: So [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Star s would
mean go to the address in s.
AUDIENCE: So why for instance, if
you [INAUDIBLE] character [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
Why, when you print out s, does it
print out the whole string and not
just the character?
That's what the printf
format code is doing for you.
When you tell printf to use percent
s, that has special meaning to printf.
And it knows to go to the first
address and not just print
the second-- the first char, but
print every character thereafter
until it sees what?
AUDIENCE: The null terminator.
DAVID J. MALAN: The null
terminating character.
So printf and percent s are special
and have been special since the Week 1.
They just know to do exactly
what you've described.
So pointer arithmetic, to be clear,
is just taking addresses and like,
doing arithmetic with them,
adding 1, adding 2, adding
3, or any other manipulation like that.
All right.
So [CHUCKLE] let's take
another stab at a meme here.
[CHUCKLE]
OK, a few of us.
All right.
All right, it's trying too hard.
So what then do we have
when it comes to strings?
Well, let's now try to
learn from these primitives
and actually trip over some mistakes
that we might otherwise make.
I'm going to go ahead
and open up a new file.
I'm going to go ahead and
call this one, compare.
So we'll save this as compare dot c.
And this will be reminiscent of
something we started doing last week.
And you've done this past week,
particularly for implementing
voting and comparing strings.
I'm going to go ahead and
make a quick program that
just compares two integers.
I'm going to put the training
wheels back on temporarily,
just so that we can get
some numbers from the user
pretty easily, including CS50
dot h and standard I/O dot h.
I'm going to do int
main void as my program.
I'm going to get an integer called
i and ask the human for that.
I'm going to get another integer
called j, ask the human for that.
And then I'm going to go ahead
and say if i equals equals j,
then go ahead and print with
printf that they're the same.
Else, if i does not equal j, I'm going
to go ahead quite simply and print out
different backslash n.
So if i equals equals
j, it should say, same.
Else, if it's different,
it should say different.
So let me go ahead and make
compare dot slash compare.
And I should see, hopefully, if I
type in say, 1, 2, they're different.
And if I instead do 1,
1, they're the same.
All right.
So it stands to reason that logically
this is pretty straightforward when
you want to compare things.
So instead of using numbers,
let me go ahead and change this.
Let me go ahead and do, say, string
s gets getString, just as before
but using getString instead
and ask the human for s.
Then give me another string, t, just
because it's alphabetically next.
And I'll ask the human for t.
And then I'm going to go ahead
and ask this question, if s equals
equals t, print same,
else, print different.
So now let me go ahead
and make compare again.
I'm going to go ahead and
type in dot slash compare.
We'll type in Emma.
We'll then type in Rodrigo.
And of course, it's
going to say different.
But if I instead run it again
and type in Emma and all right,
I'll type Emma again--
hmm, different.
Maybe it's a capitalization thing?
No.
But why as of today, are
they indeed different?
Last week we kind of waved our
hands and said, ah, they're arrays,
you have to do some stuff.
But why are they different?
AUDIENCE: They're stored
in different locations.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly, they're
stored in different locations.
So when you get a string with
getString and call it s, and then you
get another string with
t and call it t, you're
getting two different chunks of memory.
And yes, maybe the human has typed
the same thing into the keyboard,
but that doesn't necessarily
mean that they're going
to be stored in the exact same place.
In fact, what we really have here
is a picture not unlike this.
If I have a variable called s-- and I'm
just going to draw it as a box there
--and if I have a variable called t--
I'll draw it as another box
here --and I typed in Emma--
E-M-M-A --that's going to
give me somewhere in memory,
E-M-M-A backslash 0.
And I'll try it as an actual
array, albeit a little messily.
And then here, if I type
EMMA again in all caps,
it's going to end up--
thanks to getString,
at a different location in memory.
By nature of how getString works, it's
going to store anything you type in it.
And what's going to
get stored in s and t?
Well, for the sake of
discussion, let's suppose that
this chunk of memory
with the first input--
sorry --happens to be at 0x123.
And the second chunk of memory happens
to be at 0x456, just by chance.
Well, what am I
technically storing in s?
0x123.
And what am I storing in t?
0x456.
So when you say, is s equal equal t.
Is it?
Well, no.
You're literally
comparing 123 versus 456.
The computer is not going
to presumptuously go
to that address for you
unless you somehow tell it to.
Put another way, if I
instead draw these boxes,
not as actual numbers, what we really
have-- sorry --what we really have is
what we'll draw as an
arrow more generally,
just a pointer to that value.
Who really cares where the address is?
So this is why last week we
kind of waved our hand and said,
eh, you can't just compare two
strings because you probably
have to compare every character.
And that was true.
But what you're technically
comparing is indeed
the addresses of those two variables.
Any questions then on this here?
Yeah.
Sure, yes.
AUDIENCE: So you said
earlier that the, I
guess, the pointer, and
the actual thing it's
pointing are like kind of somewhere
in the memory not in a specific--
they're just somewhere, right?
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
AUDIENCE: So do you need something
that points to the point--
how does the computer
know where the pointer is?
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, how does the
computer know where these pointers are?
So that's a really good question.
And let's answer it right here.
All this time when you've been
calling getString to get a string,
you've probably been assigning it to a
variable like I have here on line six,
with string s.
But we know as of today that if we get
rid of the CS50 library, technically,
string is just synonymous
with char star.
And so both here and with t, do you
technically have char star, right?
It's just a find and replace if
we get rid of that training wheel.
Char star just means s is storing
the address of a character.
And char star t means t is storing
Ergo, all this time since the Week 1 of
CS50, what type of value has getString
been returning, even though
we never described it as such?
What must getString be returning?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: The index of the first letter.
DAVID J. MALAN: Not even the
index per se, but rather the--
AUDIENCE: It houses the memory of that.
DAVID J. MALAN: The address
of the first character.
So anytime you called getString,
getString code we wrote
is finding in your computer's
memory some free space,
enough bytes to fit whatever
the word was that got typed in.
getString then, if we
looked at its code,
is designed to return the address of
the first byte of that chunk of memory.
So getString, this whole time,
has been returning, if you will,
what's called a pointer.
But again, nuances that we didn't want
to get into in the very first week
certainly, of C programming.
All right.
Well, let's go ahead and make
this a little more concrete.
If I pull up this code, I
don't have to just check
if they're same or different, let
me just go ahead and print them out.
If I do percent p backslash n,
I can literally print out s.
And if I go ahead and print out the
same thing for t using percent p,
I can print out the value of t.
So let me go ahead and make compare.
Seems to compile OK.
And I don't know what the
addresses are in advance.
But let me go ahead and type
in, for instance, Emma and Emma.
So even though those strings
look the same notice,
it's a little subtle this time,
the first Emma's at 0xED76A0.
The second Emma's at 0xED76E0, which is
a few numbers away from the first Emma.
So that just corroborates
the instincts last week
that we can't just
compare them like that.
So what are the implications then?
Let's do one other example here.
Let me go ahead and
save this as copy dot C.
And let's try a very reasonable goal.
If I want to go ahead and get the
user's input and actually copy a string
and capitalize the string
from the user, let's see this.
So let me go ahead and give myself the
temporary training wheels again, just
so I can get a string from the human.
Let me go ahead and include standard
I/O dot h and then an int main void.
Let me do a simple
example, the goal of which
now, is to get a string from the
user and capitalize a copy thereof.
So I'm going to go ahead and do
string s gets getString and call it s,
as before.
I'm going to go ahead and
then do string t equals
s to make a copy of the variable.
And then I'm going to
go ahead and say what?
Let me go ahead and capitalize the copy.
And to capitalize the copy, I can
just change the first character
in t, so t bracket 0, to what?
I think we had toupper a while back.
Does this seem familiar?
You can call the toupper function.
And the toupper function,
if you don't recall,
you technically have
to use C type dot h.
This might be reminiscent
of the second c problem
set, where you might have used this in
Caesar, or substitution, or the like.
All right.
And now, let me go ahead and
print out these two strings.
Let me go ahead and print out s.
And let me go ahead and print out t.
So again, all I've done in this
program is get a string from the user,
copy that string, capitalize
the copy called t.
And let's just print
out the end results.
So let me go ahead and save the file.
Let me go ahead and make copy.
Seems to compile OK.
Let me go ahead and run copy.
And let me go ahead and type
in emma, in all lowercase,
deliberately, because I want to see
that t is capitalized but not s.
Hmm.
But somehow they're both capitalized.
Notice, that emma in all lowercase
ended up being both capitalized in s
and capitalized in t per
the two lines of output.
That's a bug?
Right?
I only capitalized t,
how did I accidentally
also capitalize s do you think?
Any thoughts?
Doesn't matter if I avert the
lights, I still can't see any hands.
OK, how about here in front?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So when you say t
equal s you have to [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
When I say t equals s on this line, I
am getting a second variable called t.
And I am copying s.
But I'm copying s literally.
s as of today, is an address.
After all, string is the same thing
as char star for both s and t.
And so technically, all I'm
doing is copying an address.
So if I go back to my picture
from before, this time,
if I've gone ahead and typed in an
array of emma, with all lowercase--
e-m-m-a --and then a backslash 0,
somewhere in memory using getString,
and I've gone ahead initially and
stored that in a variable called s--
and I don't care about
the addresses anymore.
I'm just going to use arrows
now to depict it graphically.
When I created a second variable
called t and I set t equal to s,
that's like literally
copying the arrow that's in s
and storing it in t, which means t
is also pointing at the same thing.
Because again, if I didn't do
this hand wavy arrow notation,
I literally wrote out 0x123.
I would have just written
out 0x123 in both s and t.
So when, in my code, I
go ahead and say, you
know what, go to the first character in
t and then go ahead and uppercase it.
Guess what the first character in t is?
Well, it's this e.
But guess what the first character
in s is, literally that same e.
So this does not
suffice to copy a string
by just saying t equals s, as it has
up until now with every other variable.
Any time you've needed a temporary
variable or a copy of something
this worked.
Intuitively, what do we
have to do probably instead
to truly copy Emma into two
different places in memory?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Probably create a char or
create a variable exactly the same size
and copy each character individually.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
So maybe we should give
ourselves a variable that
has more memory, the same
amount of memory being stored
for the original Emma, and
then copy the characters from s
into the space we've allocated for t.
And so we can actually do this.
Let me go ahead and get rid of
all but that first line, where
I've gotten s as before.
And I'm going to go ahead and do
this, I'm to say that t is a string--
but you know, we don't need
that training wheel anymore.
String, char star, even
though it looks uglier.
Let me go ahead and allocate
more memory for myself.
How do I do that?
Well, it turns out-- we've not used this
before --there's a C function called
malloc, for memory alloca.
And all it asks as input
is how many bytes you want.
So how many bytes do I want
for Emma to store her name?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: I heard 4, 5.
Why, 5?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: So we need the
null terminating character,
e-m-m-a and then backslash 0.
So that's 5.
So I could literally
hard code this here.
Of course, this feels a
little fragile because I'm
asking for any string via getString.
I don't know it's going to be Emma.
So you know what, let me go
ahead and ask a question?
Whatever the length is of
the human's input in s,
go ahead and add 1 to it
for the null character
and then allocate that many bytes.
So now my program's more dynamic.
And once I have this, well, how
can I go ahead and copy this?
Well, let me just do old school loop.
So for int I get 0, i is less than
the string length of s, i plus plus--
so this is just a standard for
loop iterating over a string
--and I think I can just do t
bracket i equals s bracket i in order
to copy the two strings.
There's a subtle bug and a
subtle inefficiency though.
Anyone want to critique how I've
gone about copying s into t?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
getString [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
This was inefficient.
We said a couple of weeks
ago this is bad design
to just keep asking the question,
what's the length the s?
What's the length of s?
So remember that we had a little
optimization a couple of weeks ago.
Let's just declare n to
equal the string length of s
and then do a condition
of i is less than n.
So we've improved the design there.
It's a little more efficient.
We're wasting less time.
There's still a subtle bug here.
How many byte-- yeah.
AUDIENCE: Aren't you not
copying the null terminator
DAVID J. MALAN: I'm not
copying the null terminator.
So every other time we've iterated
over a string, this has been correct.
Iterate up to the length but not
through the length of that string.
But I technically do
want to go one more step
this time, or equivalently,
one more step.
Because I also want to copy not just
e-m-m-a, which is str length 4--
e-m-m-a is 4 --I also want to do it
a fifth time for the null character.
So in this case, I'm
deliberately going one step
past where I usually want to go to
make sure I copy 5 bytes for Emma,
not just 4.
All right.
Let's go ahead now and capitalize Emma.
So t bracket 0 gets toupper of
Emma's first character in the copy.
And now let's go ahead and
print out both strings s
and t, just as before,
with percent s of t.
And let me make one
change, I use strlen now.
So I know I'm going to get
an error if I don't do this.
I need to use string dot h-- recall
--anytime you use string length.
So I'm going to go proactively add that.
So what's different?
This line is the same as before.
I'm getting a string from the user.
I'm capitalizing the first letter.
And these two lines are the same.
I'm just printing out s and t.
So the new idea here is, with my
malloc, am I allocating as many bytes
as I need to store a copy of
Emma, and then with this for loop
am I actually doing the actual copy?
Let me go ahead and do make copy again.
Seems to run OK.
Run dot slash copy.
Type e-m-m-a in all lowercase.
And voila, now I've
capitalized t but not s.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: When you use malloc, it's
just allocating number of bytes,
it doesn't matter where?
DAVID J. MALAN: It is just
allocating that many bytes for you.
It does not matter where.
You indeed should not care
where it is because you're just
being handed the address
and using C code,
can you just go there as you want.
All right.
Let's clean this up too.
Surely, people copy strings for years.
And in fact, we don't need
to do this for loop ourself.
It turns out we can simplify this
code a little bit by enhancing this
as follows.
It turns out, if you look in
the manual page for strings,
you can actually use
something called strcopy--
no-- without any vowels.
And you can copy into
t, the contents of s.
strcpy is a function written a
long time ago by some other human.
And they went ahead and implemented,
probably, that loop for us.
And it tightens up our code
here a little bit more.
AUDIENCE: Professor?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: What if I forgot to copy
in the null character at the end?
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
What if you forgot to copy in
the null character at the end?
It is unclear what would happen.
If there just happened to be some
bits in that location in memory
from earlier-- from some
other part of your program
--and you try printing
out s and printing out t,
you might print out many more
characters than you actually
intended-- if there's no
backslash 0 actually there.
We'll see this more and more.
Anytime you don't initialize
the value of a variable,
it's what's called a
garbage value, which means
who knows what 0s and 1s are there.
You might get lucky and it's all 0s.
But most likely it's going to
print some garbage value instead.
All right.
Any questions on this?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Is the string length
function only in the CS50 library?
DAVID J. MALAN: Is the--
which function?
AUDIENCE: String length.
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, strlen,
no, that's in string dot h.
That is a standard C thing.
AUDIENCE: OK.
If string length is a standard
function but strings are not--
DAVID J. MALAN: So what's
the dichotomy here then?
If strings don't exist--
as I've noted multiple times.
And yet, there's functions like
strcpy and strlen --what's going on?
C calls them char stars.
It is c that does not call them strings.
We, CS50, and the world in
general, calls addresses
of sequences of characters, strings.
So the only training wheel
here, really is the semantics.
We gave you a data type called string
so that in the first week of C and CS50,
you don't have to see or type
char star, which would arguably
be a lot more cryptic so early on.
It's arguably a bit cryptic today too.
Other questions?
All right, yeah.
AUDIENCE: So is char
star ID type [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Is--
say that once more.
AUDIENCE: Char star ID type [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID J. MALAN: Not all of them, but
any of them that take a string, yes.
In fact, any time you have seen
us or TF in CS50 say string,
you can literally, starting today,
change that expression to char star
and it will be one and the same.
Phew.
OK.
That was a lot.
Let's take our five minute
break here with cookies outside.
All right.
So we are back.
That was a lot.
Let me draw our attention to
what the newest feature was just
a moment ago, this notion of
malloc, memory allocation.
So recall that getString I claim
as of today, all this time,
it's just returning to you
the address of the string
that was gotten from the human.
malloc, similarly, has a return value.
And when you ask malloc for this many
bytes-- maybe it's five, for emma,
plus the null terminator,
malloc's purpose in life
is to return to you the address of
the first byte of that memory as well.
So memory alloc means, go get
me a chunk of memory somewhere,
hand me back a pointer there too.
And the onus is on me to
remember that address,
as I'm doing here, by storing it in t.
But it turns out, now that we're
taking the training wheels off,
unfortunately, we have to kind
of do a bit more work ourselves.
And there's actually a
latent bug in this program.
It turns out that I am
mal-allocating memory with this
but I'm never actually freeing it.
The opposite of malloc is a function
called free, whose purpose in life
is to hand back the memory
that you asked for so that you
have plenty of memory available
for other parts of your program
and so forth.
And long story short, if
you've ever-- on your Mac or PC
--been running a program
that maybe is a little bit
buggy --you might notice your computer
is getting slower, and slower,
or maybe it even runs
out of memory explicitly,
per some error message
--that might be quite
simply, that the programmer of
that program kept using mallc,
and malloc, and malloc to grow, and
grow, and grow their use of memory,
but they never got around to
freeing any of that memory.
So programs can run out of memory.
Your computer can run out of memory.
So it's good practice, therefore,
to free any memory you're not using.
However, how do you find this mistake?
So we've got one final
debugging tool for you.
This one's not CS50
specific like debug50.
This one is called Valgrind.
Unfortunately, it's not the easiest
thing to understand at first glance.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to run Valgrind on this
program, dot slash copy, and hit Enter.
And unfort--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
[CHUCKLE]
[COUGH]
DAVID J. MALAN: Gotcha.
OK.
I'm going to go ahead and--
there we go.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
So what you missed was
a very scary message.
So I'm going to go ahead and
run Valgrind on dot slash copy.
We see this esoteric output up
top and then my prompt for s--
because it's the same program.
It's prompting me for a string --so I'm
going to give it emma, all lowercase,
and enter.
And you'll notice now, that
there's some summary going on here
but also some mention of error.
So heap summary-- we'll come back to
that in a bit --5 bytes in 1 blocks
are definitely lost
in loss record 1 of 2.
Leak summary, I've got 5
bytes leaking in 1 blocks.
I mean, this is one of these
programs in Linux-- the operating
system that we use, that's quite common
in industry too --I mean, my god.
There's so-- there's so many more
characters on the screen that
are actually enlightening for me.
Let's see if we can focus our
attention on what matters.
Memory leaking, bad.
So how do we go about chasing
down where memory is leaking?
Well, as before, we can use help50.
And in fact, help50 will analyze
the output of Valgrind-- it's still
going to prompt me first string.
So I'm going to again, type in
emma --it's going to look at that.
It's to ask for help.
And voila, highlighted in yellow, is
a message that we, help50, recognize.
And notice our advices, looks like
your program leaked 5 bytes of memory.
Did you forget to free memory
that you allocated via malloc.
Take a closer look at
line 10 of copy dot C.
Now once you've done this a couple
of times and made the same mistake,
you can probably scroll up and glean
for yourself where the error is.
We're not revealing any more information
than is right in front of you.
And in fact, you can see here, ah,
in main on copy dot C, line 10,
there's some kind of 5 bytes in
1 blocks are definitely lost.
So there's a lot of words there but it
does draw attention to the right place.
So let me go ahead and scroll
down, focus on line 10.
And indeed, line 10 is where
I allocated the memory.
So it turns out the solution
for this is quite simple.
Down here, I'm just going
to go ahead and free
t, the address of the chunk of
memory that malloc returned to me.
So I'm undoing the effects of allocating
memory by de-allocating memory.
So now let me go ahead and run copy.
And if I run copy, it's not going
to seem to run any differently.
It's still going to work correctly.
But now if I analyze it for mistakes
with Valgrind, so Valgrind of dot
slash copy--
I'm going to again type
in emma in all lowercase
and I cross my fingers
--that indeed now, leaked
summary, 0 bytes in 0 blocks.
So unfortunately, even when all is
well, it still spits out a mouthful.
But now I see no mention
of blocks that are actually
leaked, at least in the top part here.
And we'll see more of this
over the next couple of weeks
as we use it to chase down
more complicated bugs.
But it's just another tool
in the toolkit that allows
us to detect these kinds of errors.
Let me try one other thing actually.
This is a program that
I wrote in advance.
This one is called memory dot C. And as
always, these are all on the course's
website if you'd like to tinker after.
And it's a little pointless.
It's just meant for
demonstration purposes.
So here is a program.
And it's copied from this online manual
for Valgrind, the tool I just used.
So let's see what's going on.
Here I have main, at
the bottom of my code.
I copied it.
I didn't use a prototype.
I just copied what they did.
And see here, it calls a function
called f and then returns 0.
Well what does f do? f
is this random function
up here that takes no
inputs per the void.
And in English, how would you describe
what's happening in line 7 now--
that we've introduced malloc and stars--
or pointers?
What's this doing?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: It's allocating enough
memory in [INAUDIBLE] for [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Good.
Allocate enough memory
for 10 integers-- and then
let me add-- elaborate
on your words --and then
store the address of
that chunk of memory
in a pointer called x, if you will.
So sizeof is new.
But it literally does what it says.
If you say sizeof open
paren, close paren,
and then the name of a data type, it
will tell you that an int is 4 bytes.
It will tell you that a long is 8 bytes.
It will tell you that
a char is one byte.
It's just a dynamic
way of avoiding having
to memorize those kinds of things.
So this just means give
me 10 times the size
of an int, which happens to be 4 bytes.
So that means give me 10 times
4, or 40 bytes of memory.
That's effectively an array of
memory that I can store integers in.
And malloc, per its definition, is
going to return to me the address
of the first byte of that memory.
What is now scary about
line 8, relatively speaking?
What might worry you with line
8, which is buggy, unfortunately?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
I'm doing x bracket 10 and just
arbitrarily storing the number 0.
Why?
Just because.
But 10 does not exist.
Right?
If I have 10 int, it's bracket 0, 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, not bracket 10.
So this is an example of
overflowing a buffer, so to speak.
Anytime you're talking
about memory, any time
you're talking about an array of
memory-- which this effectively
is, 10 integers, room for
10 integers back to back
to back --if you go one step too far,
that's what's called a buffer overflow,
whereby the buffer is the array.
And in fact, this would
make it even more clear.
Suppose I tried to go
there, bracket 10,000.
That is definitely not among
the bytes of memory I allocated.
That's definitely going beyond
the boundaries of my array.
But so is it true that bracket
10 is one step too far.
So what's nice about Valgrind is this.
Let me go ahead and rerun Valgrind
after compiling this memory program--
whoops --in my source directory.
Let me go ahead and make memory.
All right.
It compiled OK.
Valgrind dot slash memory--
and unfortunately, we're going
to see some crazy arcane error
messages for a moment.
But let's see what it says.
Notice here, invalid write of size 4--
that sounds bad --and 40
bytes in one blocks are--
OK, they didn't really add
an if condition in Valgrind.
--40 bytes in 1 blocks--
plural --are definitely lost.
So let's fix the second of those first.
Why am I leaking 40 bytes exactly?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: I'm never freeing it.
So I think I can get away with just
doing this here, just free the memory
after I'm done using it--
even though I'm not really
using it for anything purposeful here.
So let me try this again.
Make memory, now let me do
Valgrind dot slash memory.
And-- OK, better.
I don't see 40 bytes lost anymore.
So that's good.
But I do still have this issue.
But here's where it's sometimes
useful to understand the various data
types and their sizes.
Invalid write of size 4.
Writing in a program just
means changing a value.
And it mentioned line 8 here.
In what sense is this an
invalid write of size 4?
Well, how big is an int?
Four bytes.
You're trying to change
it arbitrarily to 0.
But I could have made that
50 or any other number.
But I'm trying to touch
an int that should not
be within the memory I
have allocated for myself.
I asked for 40 bytes, or 10 ints, but
again, because arrays are zero indexed,
this is like going one
beyond the boundary.
So let me fix this and just arbitrarily
say, let's go touch that part of it.
Let me go here and do make memory.
Let me go ahead and do
Valgrind dot slash memory.
And now, arcane output aside, notice
that that error message went away too.
So this will be helpful over
the coming couple of weeks
as we continue to use C to
implement a number of programs
that now start to manipulate memory.
It's just a tool that
helps you spot errors
that certainly, your TF
might otherwise, or that
might be causing your program to
crash, or to freeze, or to segfault--
if you've seen that yourselves before.
All right.
So that's just a tool.
Let's go ahead and transition now
to some actual use cases here.
Recall from last week that it was
pretty useful to be able to swap values.
Right?
With bubble sort, with selection sort,
we needed to be able to exchange values
so that we could put things
into the right place.
Turns out this is
pretty straightforward.
Right?
And we can actually mimic
this in the real world.
We just have opportunity for one
volunteer today, one volunteer.
Can we get a little--
OK, over here.
Yeah.
What's your name?
FARRAH: Farrah.
DAVID J. MALAN: Sorry.
DAVID J. MALAN: Vera.
FARRAH: Farrah.
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, here, come on up.
Then I can hear you up here.
OK, what's your name?
FARRAH: Farrah.
DAVID J. MALAN: Vera.
FARRAH: With an F.
DAVID J. MALAN: Fera.
FARRAH: Farrah.
DAVID J. MALAN: Farrah.
FARRAH: Yes.
Yes, OK.
Good.
Come on up.
Still come up.
[CHUCKLE] Thank you.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
[CHEERS]
OK, nice to meet you.
FARRAH: Hi, nice to meet you.
DAVID J. MALAN: Farrah.
FARRAH: Yes.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So let's go ahead here.
Let me give you this so that
you can be mic'd as well.
OK, so the goal at hand is here, I
have two glasses of colored water.
So we have some purple here.
[WATER POURING]
OK.
And we've got some green here.
[WATER POURING]
And the only goal at hand is
to do a very simple operation
like we needed to do
quite a bit last week,
which is to swap two variables
just like we swap two numbers.
So if you could go ahead and
get the purple liquid in here
and the green liquid in here, go.
[CHUCKLE]
FARRAH: Is it OK if they overlap?
DAVID J. MALAN: Ideally, no.
We want to put only purple
here, and only green here,
and no temporary store.
[LAUGHTER]
FARRAH: Oh.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK,
but you're hesitating.
Why?
FARRAH: Because you told me they
couldn't touch [CHUCKLE] and--
DAVID J. MALAN: Well, you
can touch the glasses.
But you're hesitating to swap them, why?
[CLINK]
OK, that's just cheating.
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
[CHEERS]
OK, very clever.
Supposing you can't
just move things around
in memory, what if I gave
you a temporary variable.
FARRAH: OK.
DAVID J. MALAN: Does this help?
FARRAH: Yes.
DAVID J. MALAN: So how can we now get
purple in there and green in there?
[CHUCKLE]
FARRAH: Can I put purple in here first?
DAVID J. MALAN: Sure.
FARRAH: I'm going to spill it.
DAVID J. MALAN: It's OK.
[WATER POURING]
OK.
So purple goes into the
temporary, very nice.
[APPLAUSE]
FARRAH: Thank you.
DAVID J. MALAN: Green
goes into what was purple.
FARRAH: Yes
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, good.
And then purple goes in--
from the temporary variable
into the original green glass.
Now, a proper round of
applause if we could.
OK.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
FARRAH: Thank you.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
So suffice it to say, that is the
correct way of swapping two values.
But the key detail there was that Farrah
had access to a temporary variable.
And so you would think that this
idea, simple as it is in reality,
would translate pretty
naturally to code as well.
But it turns out that's
not necessarily the case.
So it turns out that if we
wanted to swap two variables,
you might implement a
function called swap
and just take in two integers,
a and b, the goal of which
is to do the switcheroo.
Purple becomes green,
green becomes purple,
just as a becomes b, b becomes a.
And you would think that we just need a
temporary variable inside of that code
in order to make that happen.
So I would argue that the
equivalent to what Farrah did in
person, in code in C,
might look like this.
Give me a temporary
variable called temp--
or anything you want --store in it, a--
just as she stored one of the colors
in the temporary glass first, purple
--then go ahead and change the value
of a to equal the value of b--
because you've already kept a copy
of a around in a temporary variable
--then finally, store
in b what is in temp.
So that is the code equivalent of what
Farrah did using these colored liquids.
Unfortunately, it's not quite as
simple it would seem, as that.
I'm going to go ahead and open up, say,
a program that I wrote in advance here
too, called--
intentionally --no swap.
Even though you would like to
think that it does exactly that.
So notice that in this code we have--
including standard I/O dot
h --we have a prototype
for the function I just
proposed we make, swap,
that takes two ints a and b.
Here's my main function.
And I'm just going to arbitrarily
initialize x to 1 and y
to 2, just as I initialized one glass
to purple and one glass to green.
Then, just so that we can see
what's going on inside our code,
I'm just going to print out x is
such and such, y is such and such--
printing x and y --then I'm
going to call that swap function,
swapping x and y.
And then I'm going to literally
print the same phrase.
But I'm hoping that it's going to say
the opposite the second time around
if x and y are indeed swapped.
So how do I implement swap?
Well, it would seem to
be, with this same code,
using a temporary variable--
or temporary glass,
just as Farrah did for the two liquids.
Unfortunately, when I go ahead
and run this program, no swap--
and its name alone is a bit
of a spoiler --if I go ahead
and run dot slash no swap with x and
y hardcoded to 1 and 2 respectively,
you'll see that it runs, and
says, x is 1, y is 2, x is 1,
y is 2, thereby clearly failing to swap.
But if you're in agreement with
me, this feels like it's correct.
I didn't get any compiler errors.
Yet, this line of code, which uses
swap, seems to have no effect.
So what might the
intuition here or hunch
be for why this program
indeed does not swap?
AUDIENCE: So when it takes
the [INAUDIBLE] in the--
when it takes the [INAUDIBLE] whole
new variable that [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
When you pass inputs to a
function, you are effectively
passing copies of your own
values to that function.
And so when you have two variables, x
and y-- initialized to 1 and 2 --yes,
you're passing them as input to swap.
But swap is not getting actually x
and y, it's getting copies of x and y.
And per its prototype, is calling
them a and b, respectively.
So it turns out this swap
function actually does work.
It swaps a and b.
But it does not swap x and
y because those are copies.
Now this seems especially worrisome now
in so far as I cannot seem to implement
a function called swap that can even
implement bubble sorts or selection
sort.
And frankly, you might
have run into this yourself
if trying to implement this for
one of your voting algorithms.
If you needed to do a swap,
if you had a helper function,
you might have had to think about
it in a somewhat different way.
So what's the explanation
for all of this?
Well, this version of
swap doesn't actually
work because again, if we
go back to first principles,
go inside of the computer's
memory and consider
our memory is just a grid of bytes,
top to bottom, left to right.
What's really going on?
Well, it turns out that
all this time we've
been using C, my computer isn't just
arbitrarily putting things in memory
over here, over here, over here.
It actually uses your computer's
memory in a methodical way.
Certain types of data go down here.
Certain types of data go
up here, and so forth.
So what is that methodology?
Well, if we consider it just
abstractly as a big rectangle,
it turns out that if this
is your computer's memory,
at the very top of it, conceptually,
goes all of the 0s and 1s
that Clang compiled for you.
The so-called machine code, is literally
loaded into your computer's RAM when
you run dot slash something, or in a Mac
or PC, when you double click an icon,
those 0s and 1s-- the compiled code --is
loaded into your computer's memory up
here--
let's say --and it might take up
this much space for a small program,
this much space for a big program.
Below that, if your program uses any
global variables or other type of data,
those will go just below,
so to speak, the machine
code in the computer's memory.
Why?
Just because humans needed
to decide when implementing
compilers where to put stuff
in the computer's memory.
Below that is a special chunk
of memory called the heap.
And Valgrind gave it--
a teaser of this word a moment ago.
The heap is a big chunk of memory
where you can allocate memory from.
And in fact, if you call malloc--
as I did once before
--that memory is going
to come from this region
of the computer's memory,
below the global variables,
below the machine code,
because that's where Clang and compiler
designers decided to draw memory from.
So every time you call malloc, you're
carving out more and more bytes
for your program to use.
And that heap grows,
conceptually, downward.
The more memory you
use, the lower, lower,
lower it gets in this
artist's rendition.
However, there's a different portion
of memory here down below that's
used for a very different purpose.
Anytime you call a
function in your program,
it turns out that that
functions local variables end up
going at the bottom of your computer's
memory on what's called a stack.
So if you have main,
the default function,
and it has one or more arguments,
or one or more local variables,
those variables just go down
here, conceptually, in memory.
And if you call a function
like swap, or anything else,
it just keeps using more
and more memory above that.
So the heap is where
malloc gets you bytes from.
And the stack is where your
local variables go when
functions are called, bottom to top.
So let's see this in action here.
If we consider the stack alone in
the context of swapping variables
unsuccessfully, what's really
happening with code like this?
Well, on the bottom of my
memory when I call main,
I am given-- by nature of how C programs
work when compiled --a slice of memory
called a frame, a stack frame.
And this is just some number of
bytes that store maybe argv, argc,
it stores x and y, my local variables.
Any variables I have in main get
stored in this chunk of memory here.
If main calls a function, like this
swap function, that function gets
its own frame of memory, its own
slice of memory, that conceptually,
is above main.
So swap has two variables-- right--
two arguments, right, a and b.
And it also had one other variable.
AUDIENCE: Temp.
DAVID J. MALAN: Temp.
So those three values are going
to be in this frame of memory.
X and y are on the bottom, a, b,
and temp are above it in there.
So let's actually focus on this.
If we focus on main, when
my program first runs,
I have two variables, x and y.
And I initialize those
to 1 and 2, respectively.
Then the swap function gets called.
So another frame gets used on the
stack, just another bunch of bytes
are being allocated by
the computer for me.
And swap had three
variables, a, b, and temp.
The first two were its inputs,
its arguments, the third of which
was an explicit temporary
variable I gave it.
With those lines of code from before
I initialized a and b to 1 and 2,
respectively.
And notice, they are literally identical
to x and y but copies of x and y.
And then if we consider the
code, what happens next?
Well, temp is assigned a.
So temp should take on what value?
AUDIENCE: 1.
DAVID J. MALAN: Just 1.
And then second line
of code, a equals b.
So a should take on the value
of b, which means it's now 2.
And meanwhile, b equals temp means
that b should take on the value of 1.
And so now we have
successfully swapped, it
seems-- with these three lines of code
taken from my actual program --a and b.
Unfortunately, the thing about a
stack is just like in the dining hall.
When you have the stacks of Harvard
trays in the dining halls and you
keep putting news trays on
top, on top, but then they
keep getting taken from the top as well.
So just when swap is done
with its third line of code,
it's like someone has taken the
tray away and that frame disappears.
So the memory technically
doesn't go anywhere.
It's still a physical device.
But it's just no longer
allocated for my own program.
So main is still intact after
the swap function returns.
But of course, x and y have
not actually been affected.
So what's the fundamental
solution to this problem?
Swap did not work because
it was passed copies.
It was passed by value,
so to speak, when
main calls swap, passing an x and y, I
get copies of x and y called a and b.
What could I do instead?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: A little louder.
AUDIENCE: Pass by reference.
DAVID J. MALAN: Pass by
reference, and what's a reference?
AUDIENCE: Make a pointer.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So a reference is synonymous
for our purposes, with pointer.
So yeah, that's actually kind of
the germ of an idea from before.
If we now have the ability to address
things --like slap some addresses
on mailboxes--
you know what, let's not just pass
from main to swap, literally x
and y, why don't we tell swap what the
address of x is and the address of y
so that my swap code can
go to x and y, change them.
And then even when the
swap function returns,
that's fine because it went
to the right locations.
So pictorially, what I
really want to do is this.
If I take another stab at
this, I'm going to go ahead now
and reinitialize main to have
x and y equal to 1 and 2.
I'm now going to call swap.
But what I really want to
do, using pictures this time,
is I want a to point to
x and b to point to y.
I don't want them to equal
x and y because now I
can sort of follow the breadcrumbs,
or the chutes and ladder idea,
whatever metaphor works for you.
You can go from a to x, you can go from
b to y, and do the switcheroo There
So the code I'm actually
going to use now
is a little scary looking
but it just goes back
to those first principles
from the very start today.
I need to put, unfortunately, some
asterisks all over the place here.
But let's see why.
First, let me actually
back up for just a moment
and propose that the swap code I'm going
to use now is not that in no swap dot c
but in a program called swap dot c.
So in swap dot C I have almost
the same code, except this.
First of all, on line 13, I'm
no longer passing an x and y,
I'm passing in the address
of x and the address of y.
That was the key detail from
earlier today when we first
introduced ampersand.
So this means, here's the
address of x, the address of y.
It's like providing a map to
swap so that it can go there.
The syntax for defining a
function that accepts addresses
is unfortunately a little cryptic
but name of the function, like swap,
the type of pointer,
and the type of pointer.
So, int Star a means, I accept the
address of an int and call it a.
I also accept the address of
another int and I call it b.
So that's all the star
means in this context.
It's a pointer to an int.
It's a pointer to an int, both b and a.
Down here just gets a little scary
looking but it's the same exact thing.
What does star a mean?
Well, star means go to that address.
So star a means follow the arrow
to whatever a is pointing at.
And what was a pointing at?
It was pointing at x.
So this means go to the address
in a and that will reach--
that will lead you to x,
whose value I think is 1.
And that's going to store
the number 1 in temp.
The second line of code means go to b.
So if you follow the address
in b, where does it lead you?
It should lead you to what we called y.
And that y was a 2.
And star a means go to the
address in a and put whatever
was at the address in b there as well.
And then lastly, go
ahead and take temp--
which is just the number one I
claim --and go ahead and put it
at the address in b.
It's hard to see this in code.
So let's instead visualize it.
Instead, if I go back here
to these three lines of code,
here now is a correct version.
The first line of code here says go to--
whatever-- go to the address
in a and store it in temp.
So in a moment I'm going
to go to the address in a
by following this arrow down to x.
And I'm going to store
in temp the number 1.
Second line of code, I'm going
to go to the address in b.
so that's like following the
arrow, which leads me to the 2
I then follow the address
and a, which leads me to x.
And I put 2 in x.
Last line, I go to temp.
That's an easy one.
It's just the number 1.
Then I say, go to the address
in b and store temp there.
So let's go to the address
in b by following the arrow
and change it to temp.
And so now I've still
called another function.
I'm still using local variables
but these local variables
are by definition now, pointers,
addresses, or sort of treasure maps
that are leading me--
a la these arrows --to the values in
memory that I actually care about.
And so now when the
swap function returns,
it doesn't matter that a
and b and temp go away,
I have actually changed fundamentally,
what x and y themselves were.
Any questions then on that code?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
So in this case, there is nothing to
free because we did not use malloc.
So you can use addresses
without using malloc.
In this case, I'm using
the address of operator,
which just tells me where x and y is--
or--
AUDIENCE: Not with this
[INAUDIBLE],, in general,
would you use malloc [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
So if you're using malloc in a function
and it returns some chunk of memory,
how do you deal with that?
The onus is on you to
remember to somehow call free
on that same block of memory.
Case in point, getString does this.
Long story short, getString
allocates memory using malloc.
And you, up to this date
have never had to call
free on strings, that's actually because
one of the features of the CS50 library
is something called
garbage collection, where
we notice if your program quits
without freeing memory from getString.
We do it for you magically.
But you can see in the
CS50 library how you can
do exactly what you're asking about.
And, or just ask me after as well.
All right.
So this is only to say that, OK,
after all of last week's presumption
that we could actually swap
values, we can in fact do it.
So how can we go about now solving more
interesting, more real world problems?
Well, let's transition from
here to some of the power
now that we gain by understanding
these kinds of primitives.
First of all, you might have noticed
or anticipated this wasn't necessarily
the best design.
Right?
What strikes you as worrisome
about this picture at the moment?
AUDIENCE: They're gonna crash.
DAVID J. MALAN: Right, they're
going to collide with each other.
Right?
If I keep calling malloc, malloc,
malloc, malloc, per the arrow,
I claim that you're going to
keep using more and more memory.
But it turns out you're going
to keep using the stack too.
If you call function,
function, function, function,
you're going to collide or somehow
overrun each of these chunks of memory.
And in fact, recall
recursion from last week.
If you don't have that base case
and a function calls itself forever,
you have what's actually
called a stack overflow.
And those of you familiar with the
popular website for programmers, stack
overflow derives its name from
exactly that idea, the fact
that a computer if running a
program that has some bug--
whereby, function calls itself again,
and again, and again, and again,
and never stopping --you
might overflow the stack.
And there's other
incarnations of that as well.
But that's one of the forms from
which the website gets its name.
Heap overflow is the opposite.
When you keep calling malloc,
malloc, malloc, malloc, and you
just ask for so much memory
that you overwrite memory that's
being used by some of your functions.
Unfortunately, this is
just the way life is.
If you have a finite amount
of memory, there is this risk.
And this is why computers can only
use so much memory before they indeed
can't oh, load more files for you,
can't open more images for you,
or simply crash or freeze if
the problem wasn't anticipated.
Those are generally known
as buffer overflows.
So let's take off one final set
of training wheels, if you will,
all of these functions that
you asked about earlier today.
All of these functions,
getFloat, getString, getDouble,
and so forth-- from the CS50 library
--actually deal with pointers for you
and deal with memory addresses
in a way that allows you not
to have to worry about them.
Let me go ahead and implement
the same idea as getInt,
but the low level way that you would
have to do it if you didn't actually
have CS50's library.
I'm going to go ahead and
create a program called
scan f for formatted scan.
And I'm going to go ahead and
implement the following logic.
Let me go ahead and first give
myself include standard I/O dot
h-- because I'm not going
to use the CS50 library here
at all --int main void-- so I have a
default function --let me give myself
a variable x.
And let me go ahead and ask
the human for a value of x.
And then normally, I
would have done this,
getInt and get the int from the user.
If we're taking away the CS50
library, we need an alternative.
And it turns out there's
a function called
scanf and scanf is kind
of similar to printf,
where you give it a format code, which
signifies what it is you want to scan
from the user's keyboard, so to speak.
And you specify the address
of a chunk of memory
that you want to put
the user's input in.
And then I'm going to go ahead,
just arbitrarily, and print out
that the human here typed
in, for instance, that value.
So what's new here?
It's this line here.
If we did not have the CS50 library
and in turn, the getInt function,
this is the line of code you would
instead have been using since Week 1
to get an integer from the user.
It's up to you on line 5 to declare
the variable, like x and int.
It's then up to you on line 7 to
pass the address of that variable
to scanf because scanf's purpose in life
is to give the human a blinking prompt.
And provided the human types
in a number and hits enter,
that number will get stored
at that address for you.
And the reason why you need to
call a function like scanf here--
or rather, the reason that you need
to pass to scanf, the address of x,
is for the same reason as swapping.
If you want to use a helper function,
something you wrote or someone else
wrote, and you want it to
change the value of a variable,
you cannot pass it by value.
You can't just pass an x
because it will get a copy.
And that will not persist.
You have to instead use
ampersand x to pass the address
of x so that the function, swap--
or in this case, scanf
--can go to that address
and put some value there for you.
Unfortunately, what scanf
does not do is if the user
types in Emma instead
of an int, it's quite
possible the program
will choke, or crash,
or behave in some unpredictable way.
There's no error checking
built in to scanf in this case.
But let's try another thing.
It's not that interesting
to read in just an int.
Let's try to read in
something like a string.
So I could give myself a string s--
although we know that there
is no such thing as string.
That's technically a
char star or the address
of a character called s --let me go
ahead and prompt the human for string
s here.
And let me go ahead and
read into that string using
the percent s format code, the value s.
And then let me go ahead and print out
what the human typed for us, s colon
that.
So what am I doing here?
Line 5 is saying, give
me a variable called s
that's going to store the
address of a character.
Line 6 just says, s colon, like print.
It's a prompt for the human,
nothing too interesting there.
scanf is this function
that takes the format code
so it knows what to read from the user's
keyboard and the address of a place
to put it.
And char star-- this is an
address --I don't need to use
ampersand because unlike an
int, char star is already,
by definition, a pointer or an address.
And then lastly, I just print
out whatever the human typed in.
Unfortunately, let's
see what happens here.
Let me go ahead and save this.
Make scanf-- give myself a
bigger terminal window --enter.
Oh, my goodness.
All right.
So what's wrong here?
Variable s is uninitialized
when used here.
So Clang is trying to
protect me from myself.
I haven't initialized s to an address.
Where do we want to put Emma's name?
Well, maybe we could do like
0x123, or something like this,
or in the absence of that--
if you don't know the
address in advance --null
is the convention to
which it's alluding to.
N-U-L-L is a special pointer that
means there is no pointer there.
It's all 0s.
Let me try this again, make scanf--
OK, it seemed to work --dot slash scanf.
Let me go ahead and type in Emma.
Hmm.
Emma is null.
Let me try that again.
So Emma is the Head CA for CS50--
let's type a longer string --null.
So nothing even seems to fit, not
even the first letter of her name.
So why is that?
And actually, sometimes we
can get the program to crash.
Let's see, a little
weird but, let's do this.
[CHUCKLES]
So a longer string--
slightly creepy now, perhaps.
But, OK.
--enter.
Dammit.
Emma not found.
OK, not what I intended.
Let's do this once more.
Oh, my god.
Now, my histor-- OK, dot slash
scanf, Emma, Emma, Emma, Emma, enter.
Dammit.
[LAUGHTER]
OK, well, either way it's broken, which
was the only point I'm trying to make.
[LAUGHTER]
So why is this not actually working?
Well, you have to remember
what char star s means.
This means, give me a
variable in which I can
store the address of a chunk of memory.
Null, at the moment is
a symbol that means,
like, there is no memory allocated yet.
So technically speaking, I've not
actually allocated any memory for Emma
to actually be stored in.
So really what I should be
doing is something like this.
If I know in advance, a
little presumptuously,
that the human's going
to type in Emma, let
me go ahead and give myself
an array called s of size 5
and then pass this in on line 7.
So in short, there's this--
there's this relationship
between arrays and pointers
that's sort of been latent
throughout today's discussion.
An array is just a chunk of
memory back-to-back-to-back.
A string is just a sequence of
characters back-to-back-to-back.
A string is technically an address
of the first byte of that memory.
And so sort of by
transitivity, a pointer
can be viewed as the same thing as
an array, at least in this context.
So let me go ahead and allocate
myself an array of five characters.
It turns out that Clang will treat the
name of an array just like a pointer
if you use it in this
context to scanf, passing
in the address of the
first byte in that array.
So now if I go ahead and make
scanf with this third version
and do dot slash scanf
and type in Emma--
that's four characters.
I know safely I'm leaving room
for the null terminator --now
it's storing Emma's name successfully.
And if I go ahead and do this here,
emma, in lower case, that works.
And if I get a little greedy and do like
Emma Humphrey, first name, last name,
Hmm.
It didn't work.
But why might that be?
I haven't allocated
enough space for her name.
I'm lucky frankly, that
the program's not crashing.
But if I loaded as I was trying
to do, a big enough paragraph
of text, my program outright
might crash or segfault,
so to speak-- an error message
that you'll likely see this week
or next as we continue to use memory.
Let me do one final
example now because there's
one sort of power we now
get that we have the ability
to talk in terms of memory addresses.
I'm going to go ahead and make a
program here, reminiscent of last week,
called phone book dot
C, whose purpose in life
is going to be to store
some information in a file--
for the very first time.
I'm going to use the CS50
library just to put the training
wheels back on briefly so I can
get input from the human easily.
But I'm going to go ahead then and use
the string library and standard I/O,
int main void.
And I'm going to go ahead
and do the following.
I'm going to go ahead
and open a file called
file, using a new function called
fopen, phone book dot CSV, a.
Now what is going on here?
Well it turns out, now that
we know pointers-- or starting
to get comfortable with pointers
over the next couple of weeks
--notice that I can actually use a new
data type-- it's weirdly capitalized--
all caps, FILE.
But I can say, give me a pointer to
a file and call it lower case file.
So this is just a variable called FILE,
that effectively, for today's purposes,
is going to store the
contents of a file for me.
It's not technically doing that but
that's a reasonable mental model
for now.
fopen takes, as its first argument,
the name of the file you want to open.
And the second argument is either r,
or w, or a-- r, for read w, for write,
a, for append--
to just keep adding to a file.
The goal at hand is
to write a phone book
program that lets me type
in a human's name and number
and just keep appending
it to a text file,
like a database that I can store if I
want to keep track of people's phone
numbers.
fopen, by definition, is going
to return a pointer to that file.
So let me go ahead now
and do the following.
First, I'm going to go ahead and give
myself a name, although I don't really
need to use string per se.
I'll use char star name.
But I am going to use getString just
to save myself some trouble here,
asking the human for their name.
I am going to then ask the human for
their number using getString as well.
But again I could use scanf If I want.
But it's going to require
more error checking today.
And now I'm going to
go ahead and do this.
It turns out that besides
the function printf,
there's another function called
fprintf, which means file printf.
You can print literally to a file.
So I'm going to go ahead here
and now do print to this file,
print a string, and a comma, and
another string, and then a new line.
And I'm going to go ahead and print out
someone's name and then their number.
And then down here I'm
going to close the file.
So a bunch of new lines,
but this one in short--
I'll comment it --open file,
get strings from user, print--
that is write --strings to
file, and then close file.
So new functions but pretty
straightforward at least,
conceptually, I would argue.
It's terms of what's happening even
though the syntax is a little strange.
But I did deliberately choose this
file name, phone book dot CSV.
Does anyone know what a CSV is?
Yeah, comma separated variables.
It's like a very--
comma separated values, it's a
very simple spreadsheet format
that you can open in Excel, or Apple
Numbers, or other tools like that.
So I can actually make my own
CSV files kind of like this.
Let me go ahead and make phone book.
All right, that seemed to work.
Let me go ahead and do
dot slash phone book.
And now it's asking for
a name, so I'll do Emma.
And then I think her number
last week was 555-0100, enter.
But notice this, if I type ls,
besides all of the programs
we've written today, there's also
this phone book dot CSV file.
And in fact, let me open
up phone book dot CSV.
And there's Emma's name
and number in a file.
Let me go ahead and run
it once more and this time
do Rodrigo, like last
week, 617-555-0101, enter.
And voila, his name just
appeared in the file.
We'll do one more.
So Brian was 617-555-0102, enter.
And the CSV file is getting
updated in real time.
And now if I actually go and
download this file from the IDE
by control clicking or
right clicking on it,
that ends up in my downloads folder.
And if I go ahead and click on this--
if you have something like Numbers
or Microsoft Excel installed and
you use it for the very first time--
you'll see that it's opened
up a spreadsheet containing
those names and those numbers.
So if you've ever needed to do a sort
of data science-like analysis of data,
you can actually write code
that generates the data for you
in a CSV format and gives you these,
perhaps, familiar, rows and columns.
But let me do one final example now
that will motivate this coming week's
problem set challenges.
So I'm going to go ahead now and
write a final program that-- whose
purpose in life is to detect this.
I have here in front of me a picture
of Brian [LAUGHTER] in JPEG format.
And I have a cat in GIF format--
which doesn't work in the IDE
but let me go ahead and download
it locally --does look like this.
So it's this guy from
a couple of weeks ago.
But both-- one is in GIF
format, one is in JPEG,
which if you're familiar
from file formats
are just different types of images.
Let me go ahead and write a program
real quick that is called JPEG dot c.
And its purpose in life is just to
check if a file passed by its name
at the command line is a JPEG or not.
I'm going to go ahead and
include standard I/O dot h.
I'm going to call my function
int main, but not void.
This time I'm going to use
int argc, like last week,
and string argv open paren--
open bracket closed bracket.
But you know what?
We don't need strings anymore.
This is actually what you've been typing
sort of unknowingly the past week when
you were using command line arguments,
or the past couple of weeks.
Now I'm going to go ahead
and do a quick error check.
If argc does not equal 2,
I'm just going to. quit.
I want the human to type,
not just the program's name,
but one other word as well.
I then want to go ahead
and open up the file
that the human typed in at the prompt--
which I claim is going to be the
second word they type --so argv 1.
And I want to read it this
time, not append line-by-line,
I just want to read
it from the beginning.
And the key-- keyword for that is r.
And then I'm going to go ahead and
actually do a little error check.
If file equals equals null--
we haven't seen this before
--but if fopen, if malloc,
if getString return error
conditions, they actually
return the special value null.
But for now, let me just go ahead
and say, something went wrong.
I'm going to return 1.
But we won't worry too
much more about it for now.
So at this point I have opened file.
I have ensure user ran
program with two words
at prompt, that's our argc use there.
Now let's go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and give
myself an array of 3 bytes.
And I'm going to go ahead and
use a function called fread--
And we'll see more of
this in the assignment.
So this is deliberately quick.
--I pass in his argument, the array,
the number of bytes I want to read,
how many times I want to read
those bytes, and then the file
from which I want to read those bytes.
So that was a mouthful.
But collectively, these two lines
of code read 3 bytes from file.
It just literally reads the
first 24 bits, or 3 bytes--
each of which is 8 bits --from the file.
And why am I doing this?
Well, it turns out, check if
bytes are 0xFF, 0xD8, 0xxFF.
So again, coming full
circle to hexadecimal,
it turns out that in the documentation
for the JPEG image format,
the first 3 bytes of
any JPEG in the world--
any photograph you've ever
taken with your camera--
start with FF, then D8, then FF.
This is a so-called magic number
that the designers of the JPEG format
just decided, use this as a sort of clue
at the beginning of the file that hey,
here comes a JPEG image.
So how do I do this?
It's actually pretty simple,
if bytes 0 equals equals 0xFF--
I can literally type
hexadecimal in C --or byte--
rather, and bytes 1 equals 0xD8,
and bytes 2 equals equals 0xFF,
then it turns out, it's probably a JPEG.
There are some conditions.
We'll explore in the problem set.
So I'm just going to
say maybe it's a JPEG.
But if that's not true, I am
going to say with confidence,
no, it's not a JPEG if those
first 3 bytes are not that.
And then for arcane
reasons, I technically
need to make this
what's called unsigned,
which means it's a number from 0 to
255, instead of negative 128 to 127.
But let me wave my hands at that, just
so that we get this code right for now.
I'm going to go ahead and
run JPEG and fail miserably.
What did I do wrong?
fopen is the name of
that function-- sorry--
make JPEG, good.
And now I'm going to
run JPEG on my Brian
image, which is in my source for
directory on the course's website.
He is maybe a JPEG.
And then I'm going to go ahead and do
JPEG on source for cat dot GIF, which
is no, not a GIF, which is to say that
once you have the ability to express
pointers, we now have the programmatic
capabilities, not only to write files,
but read them as well.
Now what can we actually
use that information for?
Well it turns out what we'll be doing
now, this coming week and beyond,
is exploring a number of
features here of what's
called file I/O. Long story short,
if you've ever wondered really
what an image is-- we talked
briefly about this in Week 0
--this is an image.
But it's in binary, 0s and 1s.
Does anyone know what this image is of?
AUDIENCE: A smiley face.
DAVID J. MALAN: Well, how did you-- are
a nonzero number of you looking ahead
on the slides?
Because yes, it's a smiley face.
And you would only know this
by assuming that 1 represents
a white pixel, 0
represents a black pixel,
and if we effectively
have a grid of bits--
1's and 0's --this from far back kind of
looks like the simplest possible smiley
face.
So that's an image, or
a bitmap, a map of bits,
that represent the pixels in an image.
So with problem set four, what
we're going to start to do
is explore the world of
forensics, first and foremost.
And we have a few minutes left.
And we're going to spend one of
them on this little teaser here,
which is something that you might see
typically on your typical CSI type
shows.
And let's motivate it as follows.
If we could dim the
lights for this clip.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- --we know?
- That at 9:15, Ray
Santoya was at the ATM.
- OK, so the question is,
what was he doing at 9:16?
- Shooting the 9
millimeter at something.
Maybe he saw the sniper.
- Or was working with him?
[BEEPS]
- Wait, go back one.
- What do you see?
[TYPING]
[BEEPS]
- Bring his face up, full screen.
- His glasses.
- There's a reflection.
[TYPING]
[BEEPS]
[CHUCKLE]
[LAUGHTER]
- [INAUDIBLE] baseball team.
That's their logo.
- And he's talking to
whoever's wearing that jacket.
- We may have a witness.
- To both shootings.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So at the risk
of ruining a lot of TV for you,
this is not a thing.
You can't just say enhance
and things get enhanced.
Why?
Well, here's that same picture of Brian.
And let's [LAUGHTER] look
at this glint in his eye.
Let's see what's there.
If we could zoom in on this, and
then zoom in on this, and then
zoom in on this.
This is all of the data
that is in Brian's eye.
There is no enhance at
that point, when you're
looking at just pixels represented
by colors, a la Week 0.
So what you'll do for
this coming week in fact--
in fact, let's actually
make this more real.
If we could go back to the
clip here for just 20 seconds,
if we could dim the lights once more.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Magnify that death sphere.
[BEEPS]
Why is it still blurry?
- That's all the resolution we have.
Making it bigger
doesn't make it clearer.
- It does on CSI Miami.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID J. MALAN: So with
that said, this week,
will we understand all
the more how images work?
And here for instance, is a
shot of the Charles River.
And for the first part of the problem
set, we implement a number of Instagram
like filters, understanding
how an image is represented
and how you therefore can transform it.
For instance, first, into grayscale,
by writing your own grayscale
filter, into sepia, into--
reflecting it on the opposite from
left to right, blurring an image,
even still.
And if you're feeling more
comfortable, to do something
called edge detection,
which finds all of the edges
within a particular picture.
More than that, will
you actually implement
code that recovers JPEG files?
We've been taking some photographs
of people, places, and things.
Unfortunately, we accidentally
deleted those photos
but first made a forensic image of
the memory card from the camera, which
we will then provide to
you so that you can write
code in C that recovers
all of the seemingly
lost JPEGs from that forensic image.
And last but not least,
it would not be a CS class
without a little bit of CS humor.
We thought we'd end on this one note,
a joke that you will perhaps now get.
[LAUGHTER]
All right.
That's it for CS50.
We'll see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]